Manuel González González

Address: D Street #169 Ramey, Aguadilla Puerto Rico Mobile No.: 787-608-9513

Email: manuel.gonzalez3@upr.edu

Online C.V.:www.linkedin.com/in/manuelgonzalez3h

PROFILE

I have a doctorate in Psychology and a master's in Public Health in Biostatistics. My main interests are in statistics, quantitative methods, cognition and emotion. My research experience has focused on research designs, data processing, statistical analysis, and grant writing in psychological and educational research.

EDUCATION

Philosophy Doctorate in General Psychology

2019

Emphasis: Methodology and Quantitative Research University of Puerto Rico Río Piedras Campus

Master's in Public Health in Biostatistics

2014

University of Puerto Rico Medical Sciences Campus

Honors: Cum Laude

GPA: 3.65

Bachelor's in psychology

2008

University of Puerto Rico Mayagüez Campus

Honors: Cum Laude

GPA: 3.33

STATISTICAL AND DATA ANALYST PROJECTS

CAEP Accreditation of Teacher Preparation Program

2019 –

Interamerican University at Fajardo

School of Education and Social Sciences

Data analysis, data management and statistics consultation through Bulwark Analytics, LLC. Collaborated in preparing report for accreditation agency.

Neurocognitive Abilities and Math Achievement in Puerto Rican Students

2018 -

Principal Investigator: Nilda Medina, Ph.D.

Ana G. Méndez Carolina Campus

Project funded by National Institute of Health and the Puerto Rico IDeA Network Biomedical Research Excellence (PRINBRE) program. Responsibility included designing data entry protocols, data processing, statistical analyses, and collaborating in the dissemination of research findings.

Competency Development Approaches: Increasing STEM Awareness and Retention to Narrow the Achievement Gap of Hispanic Students

2017 -

Principal Investigator: Marielis E. Rivera Ruiz, Ph.D.

School of Sciences and Technology,

Ana G. Méndez Carolina Campus

An HSI-STEM project funded by the US Department of Education. Responsabilities included collaborating in data collection procedures, data processing, statistical analysis, and collaborating in the elaboration of progress reports.

Assessment of neurocognitive abilities in children with and without language 2016 – 2017 impairment

Principal Investigator: Nilda Medina, Ph.D.

Ana G. Méndez Carolina Campus

Project funded by National Institute of Health and the Puerto Rico IDeA Network Biomedical Research Excellence (PRINBRE) program. Duties included designing data entry protocols, data processing, statistical analysis, and collaborating in the disseminations of research findings.

The use of a Neuro-Cognitive Diagnosis Model for Specific Learning Problems 2014 – 2015 in Children at Risk of School Desertion

Principal Investigator: Mary A. Moreno, PhD.

Institute for Psychological Research,

University of Puerto Rico, Rio Piedras

Provided statistical and methodological consultation for ongoing research tasks including data analysis, database creation and processing. Presented and communicated findings to the research team and in international conferences. Supervised undergrad volunteers.

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Doctoral Dissertation December 2019

Title: Associations of *Emotion Dysregulation and Risk Behaviors in Puerto Ricans young adults.* Mentor: Nelson Cruz, Ph.D.

This study aims to validate and obtain initial psychometric properties of an emotion dysregulation measure including the association of these constructs with risk behavior criteria.

Independent Research Project

2013 - 2019

Title: Methodological and Thematic Tendencies in Dissertations from 3 Psychology Graduate Program in Puerto Rico: "Doctoral Orphans" and Independent Researchers?

Co-Investigators: Nayra Rodríguez, Ph.D., Giselle Cordero, Ph.D.

This study aims to survey the methods, data analysis, and themes from a stratified sample of dissertations from 2004-2012.

Master's Capstone Project

March 2014 – August 2014

Title: Survey Comparing the Prevalence of Respiratory and Cardiovascular Diseases in a Community Exposed to Industrial Contaminants and an Un-

Exposed Community

Principal Investigator: Gilberto Ramos, Ph.D.

University of Puerto Rico, Medical Sciences Campus

Capstone project required for master's degree in Public Health in Biostatistics. Duties included designing survey questionnaire, gathering data, statistical analysis and writing reports.

Research Assistant August 2009 –

Title: Pilot Study: Validation and Psychometric Properties of the Depressive Symptoms Spectrum Assessment Inventory in Youth (INEESD, in Spanish)

Principal Investigator: Eduardo Cumba-Avilés, PhD

Institute for Psychological Research (IPsi)

Reviewed literature, administered questionnaires, tests, and transcribed focus group interviews with adolescents in Puerto Rican schools.

Research Assistant 2005 – 2007

Title: Study of system level designs methodologies for implementing SAR

support algorithms

Principal Investigator: Ana Nieves Rosa, PhD

Centro de Investigaciones Sociales Aplicadas (CISA)

University of Puerto Rico Mayagüez

Collaborated in the development of behavioral measures and video analysis to establish usability

and learning pattern in programming SAR chips

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Lecturer 2018 – 2019

School of Health Sciences

Ana G. Méndez University

Have taught the following courses: Introduction to Biostatistics (PUHE201), Statistics Applied to Social Sciences (SOSC250), and Introduction to Statistics (STAT300)

Graduate Teaching Assistant

January 2010 –

June 2012

June 2010

Supervisor: Carmen Rivera, Ph.D.

Department of Psychology,

University of Puerto Rico Río Piedras

Taught practice labs in the use of IBM SPSS for two psychology graduate courses: PSIC 6006 "Statistical Applications to Psychology" and PSIC 6305 "Statistical and Advanced Methodological Designs".

OTHER EXPERIENCES

Co-founder Bulwark Analytics, LLC.

December 2018 -

Co-Founders: Yamil Ortiz, PhD. & Mario Bermonti, MA.

Provide statistical & methodological consulting services to research projects, educational institutions and not-for-profit organizations. Additionally provide education and training services to in statistics and methodology to staff and personnel

Assistant Grant Writing

January 2012 – June 2012

Supervisor: Suzanna Engman, Ph.D. Chancellor's Office IDEAS Task Force, University of Puerto Rico Río Piedras

Provided statistical and methodological consultation for institutional grants and proposal, reviewed data and literature, and identified new funding opportunities.

SKILLS

- Statistical Programming in R
- Proficient in the use of IBM SPSS statistics
- Expertise in applied statistics and quantitative methods in psychology, public health, and education
- Excellent written and verbal communication skills in Spanish and English

TRAINING AND QUALIFICATIONS

- 34 Graduate Credit Hours in Statistics
- 10 Graduate Credit Hours in Research Method Designs
- 8 Graduate Credit Hours in Program Evaluation
- Bachelor's level 6 Credit Hours in Research Designs
- Bachelor's level 6 Credit Hours in Statistics,
- 9 Credit Hours in Mathematics up to Differential Calculus,
- 3 Credit Hours in Computer Programming

CERTIFICATIONS

- R Programming by Johns Hopkins University on Coursera. Certificate earned on June 28, 2015
- Getting and Cleaning Data by Johns Hopkins University on Coursera. Certificate earned on August 1, 2015
- Exploratory Data Analysis by Johns Hopkins University on Coursera. Certificate earned on August 29, 2015

PUBLICATIONS

Cordero-Arroyo, G., **González-González, M.**, Bermonti-Pérez, M., & Moreno Torres, M. (2018). Intervención Neuropsicológica para Estudiantes con Inatención, Hiperactividad y Dificultades en Lectura. Revista Puertorriqueña de Psicología, 29(2), 254-268.

Díaz-Flores, W., **González-González, M.**, & Moreno Torres, M. (2018). Desempeño en el Cognitive Assessment System 2 Español de estudiantes de Puerto Rico identificados como dotados. Revista Puertorriqueña de Psicología, 29(2), 316-330.

Moreno-Torres, M. A., Ortiz-Ortiz, Y., **González-González, M.** (2016). Teachers training on neurocognitive processes to address school dropout associated with academic achievement. *Revista Puertorriqueña de Psicología*, 27(2), 304-318.

SELECTED PRESENTATIONS AND POSTERS

Moreno-Torres, M.A., **González-González, M.**, Ortiz-Ortiz, Y. (2015, September). School Desertion and Academic Achievement: Teacher's Workshop in Neurocognitive Processes that Impact Learning. Poster presented at Avances en Investigación y Acción con la Niñez y Juventud, University of Puerto Rico, Mayaguez Campus. [**Role: Statistical Analysis**]

Díaz-Flores, W., Bermonti, M. E., **González-González, M,** Fonseca-Cardona, N., Moreno-Torres, M. A. (2015, February). *Relationship between Executive Function and Academic Achievement in Hispanic Children*. Poster presented at National Association of School Psychologist, Orlando, Florida. [**Role: Statistical Analysis**]

Ortiz-Ortiz, Y., Cordero-Arroyo, G., **González-González, M.**, Díaz-Flores, W., Moreno-Torres, M. A. (2015, February). *Temperament and Executive Function in Hispanic Children with ADHD*. Poster presented at National Association of School Psychologist, Orlando, Florida. [Role: Statistical Analysis]

Rodríguez-Soto, N. C., **González-González, M.,** & Arroyo-Cordero, G. (2013, September). *Themes and methodologies used in the dissertations of 3 Psychology graduate programs in Puerto Rico metropolitan area from 2000-2012: Pilot Study*. Poster presented at "5ta Jornada Estudiantil de Investigación en Psicología", San Juan, PR. [**Role: Co-Principal Investigator**]

González-González, M., González, M., & Camacho, I. (2007, November). Learning Tendencies: In the Development of Algorithms for SAR Images in FPGA's Platforms. Poster presented in Lockheed & Martin, Phoenix, Arizona.